[Music]
hello hello schen how are you it's Frank
defus yes I'm all right I'm glad I was
able to get the number and get you in
there I know it's getting late there
where you are now and you probably want
to get home for the weekend oh it's no
problem I work very late so I start
early and not very early so I work late
I I work late too I I got the last show
up last night around midnight so uh okay
it's good to do another one with you
today and I'm glad we finally have a
chance to talk I've visited your website
many times I'm very impressed with the
work that you're doing with holography
especially with the full color yes well
how did that come
about oh well I started very early with
it but only with two colors so but now
uh I have a good uh setup and uh we make
uh about uh 400 color Holograms each
year with the students mhm small size uh
the ones you have on your website they
look like they're probably 8 by1 or
larger yeah 8 by 10 8 by 10 all of them
that's a maximum well I've tried a
larger one but um the setup is too small
for uh for uh very big Holograms what
are you using like a a 4x8 Newport table
there uh it's a stone table in fact oh
no kidding isn't that something that's
beautiful work too now you you're using
all gas lasers with that I presume yeah
I have an aan no not an Aron a helium
cadmium laser I have a diet pumped jug
laser and a helium neon Laser Now the
course that you run there what type of
students take that
course and well I I have several uh
electric engineering and uh uh well the
different
uh
well we have had Al for engineering uh
physics
and so that is the kind of uh students
and I have also a special course for uh
holographs or
people especially interested in
holography yes I I would assume that the
course runs as a um a separate course to
the physics and electrical engineering
course but also as a uh primary course
for the students who would wish to take
uh holography as their primary
study yeah something like that well I
mean most of the Holograms are made with
a uh with engineering physics or
uh such type of students but I have a a
a small group
that's especially interested in in
holography yeah and so they make
different kinds of Holograms like
rainbow Holograms and and uh colar and
and
ordinary uh Holograms like transmission
Holograms and reflection Holograms in
one color now would your students once
they've completed this course and
they've received their degree would they
then go out into the
workforce uh the workforce yes would
they then go to try and get jobs doing
holography in your country well in in
our country our country is isn't very
big uh the number of pupils the the
number of persons in Sweden is 8 million
so so it's not very easy to to find a
job in holography here now how long have
you been involved with holography and
how did you get started well I was
interested in holography already and I
started in
6869 and uh well I I I was interested in
stereoscopy and photography and so on
so uh I tried to make uh in fact a film
in in three dimensions and such things
so uh I I I was amazed by the
pictures and the holographic pictures so
I I I started very early was it very
difficult getting the university to to
set up a holography lab or were they
very willing to do
that well
uh well I it was it was not very not
very difficult to to get a lab like this
yeah in the beginning and
then uh then we expanded a bit
to then so now I have in fact uh two
large tables and one small and
uh uh we working in three separate rooms
and we have a lab
nearby so it's a very nice I I I think
that it would be good if I could have
international students to to use the lab
more uh I think it's uh it would be nice
I tried I have had some some
International students would the lab be
open for people to rent the studio to do
work in
it uh I I I don't think it's uh well
it's possible to to do that maybe yes
why don't you tell a little a little bit
about the university
itself this is Lund Lund University yes
L University we have a technical part
and we have
another we have two parts so so one is
just in in
technical technical faculty
yeah yeah and the plates you're using
are are they're they're called Ultima
plates right yes that's right yeah and
how how's the response of those
plates the response yeah as far as your
exposure times working with them it's uh
I mean uh in fact uh I think there was a
reduction in the time of 3 to four
compared to Russian plates I used the
Russian slavish plates before mhm what
are the Holograms that are on your
website the full color Holograms they're
used is that the
Ultima some some are uh Russians and
optimate yes yeah I um I've only seen
one full color hologram and that was
many years ago and I have not had a
chance to even see one in front of me
I've seen them on websites but I I was
in Montreal uh many years ago I think it
was a show called images in time and
space and that was the only time I've
ever seen in front of me a full color
hologram okay okay well I I I have for
the moment I have a setup for doing a 20
by 20 5 cm
hologram uh and I I have already tested
one one plate and so uh and now the the
the French plates are very good and I
hope uh I hope I will get a very clear
plate I already had one so I I I trying
another uh object just now uh with the
um the ual diagram and the setup that
you have on your website I see the uh
multiple laser beams passing through the
beam Splitters and being combined is
there anything that you need to do to
the beam intensity what's the ratio uh
for the RGB for the red green and blue
what's what's the ratio to one another
that folks would be interested in
hearing
about well it's dependent on if I use
the DI laser or the uh or the helium
neon I I mean I made some experiments
with that and um
but the the balance is merely nearly 3 3
33 33 for the moment that is okay the
the
D in in the plate is they are optimized
for that so oh that that's very clever
so the dyes and the plates are optimized
so that you use the same
amount of power about the same yeah yeah
that's uh I mean there is a difference
uh between the red uh di laser and helan
Laser yeah the wavelength difference
yeah I think it's 63
638 I see I see so you'd be closer to
that with the heene than you would the
diode but I mean the no no no I mean the
DI laser is
638 oh I see okay but I don't know
exactly where is the optimum and in fact
I mean to compensate sometimes for the
coherence
loss I have to uh I have to change your
radios I
see so that I mean the background will
not be uh you can see maybe in some uh
uh Holograms there is a green blue
background because the the coherence
length
doesn't uh I mean the cerence doesn't
reach the back in the isn't that
interesting I'll have to go back on
there and and and take a look at that
that's interesting well it's I
mean but if I have a I I I made this
spring I made one with a dire laer when
there was no modood hop in it and then I
uh the the background was white I see
white yes but when I make larger
Holograms I think it's more important
that
um that I have a good coherence length
that is why I try to get the dire laser
working well let's say you're doing an
8x10 plate um what's your exposure time
running for an 8x10 plate on your system
is a is by no 8 by 10 inches uh well
let's say 30 by 40 cm or so I've had
some plates that size but they only 20
by 25
okay uh the exposure time
uh well something like 3 minutes or so
okay total I I have a have you
seen uh I have an uh
paper on the I think you were in the
conference in uh weren't you in uh
Austria
no okay no I can send you uh the EXP the
the paper on the set up oh okay did you
have some Holograms in
there in in the conference did you
provide a paper and a few yeah yeah yeah
I showed the Holograms and and uh
present to the set up oh okay yeah I
think I've been to the website of the
the last conference but uh and I've I've
seen maybe you can get directly that uh
the digital version of yeah yeah I think
I may have it bookmarked somewhere I
don't remember a downloadable document
on it though if you want to send it to
me i' I'd be happy to receive that and
look look through that and if you want
to I can include it on the web page with
this show so other folks can download it
too okay yeah so send yeah send that to
me and I'll put that up with the uh with
the show when it goes up uh probably
about two weeks I guess we'll go up with
this mhm so how many students do you
have in your class typically
there I mean we we
make we we have eight students and they
make uh eight Holograms in four hours
wow yeah you
it's I mean this is
they I mean this is part of half the
time they use for the the color
Holograms and and half the time they
study already made Holograms so I see so
they get their own Holograms and so they
can put up the Tob well that sounds like
a great class I don't think we have
anything like that here no no probably
not I haven't heard no yeah I know I
know some colleges are just setting
stuff up with laser pointers let alone
the type of uh setup that you have
although there's a couple high schools
actually uh that have some great Labs uh
there's one in Florida Jacksonville uh
Florida which is Englewood High School
they have a great holography lab for
kids but of course they not doing full
color work but uh it's a beautiful setup
but do you have a color LA or a
holographic lab for kids too yeah I I I
bring students in to uh do holographic
workshops here sure yeah it's not too
busy in the summertime like it is in the
uh the school season when kids are
working on science fair projects and
things like that but it's it's nothing
as complex as uh doing color work I mean
a lot of them are middle school students
and high school students and we come in
and uh do the setup and just do a simple
you know either single beam or split
beam hologram depending on their project
yeah okay in fact I'm for the moment I'm
just sitting at the computer I was
working on I'm working with digital
holography too oh that's interesting
tell us a little about that and for the
moment I I tried a very long time to get
a the image and it just appeared on the
on the computer here so how now you'll
take that uh you'll take that Digital
Data and what will you do with that uh
well we we have a project we try to make
it digital
microscope in
fact uh we have a a digital camera and
uh uh we are studying face I mean with
holography that you you get the
information the face information also
and that that information is very
important in you can uh measure uh
differences in in refractive index and
so on so I
see so you're not you're not actually
generating a hologram from that data yet
and not well I I can well what what you
know about digital holography or I
wouldn't say I'm an expert on it but I'm
familiar with it yeah yeah so in fact
what we just um put the screen a virtual
screen in the field and we we can change
the position of this screen MH and see
where the image is focused I see and so
um and also you you get the the face
information from the Hologram I see I
see and this is important this is all
part of your students projects or is
this a personal project of your own well
we we uh are running in in a way a
company we're starting a company on it
oh really what's what's the name what's
going be the name of the company the the
name is
the uh
F
uh I don't F company okay p p h i okay
face holographic Imaging great yeah
great and what will the final product be
that you'll be manufacturing and
providing yeah we we have a prototype of
a a digital uh
microscope I see I see for the moment so
we we will continue we have the first
version of it and it ties into
holography the there's a hologram
involved which is an optical
Element no there is no Optical element
it's it's a CCD I see okay so
uh so we we have
uh just just we record the interference
field between uh reference beam and the
object field I see and that's captured
on the CCD yeah and then we reconstruct
it in a in a digital form wow what's
what's the resolution of that
CCD uh it's
um yeah the the resolution is something
like uh 10 micr
wow but
um you can
um
uh you can over sample and so you can
get finer details I see I see that's
incredible well you have a lot of stuff
going on there
yeah so for the moment we we
also I I have had a student working on
on the Hol ol
graphy inline holography with
a a terawatt
laser they make
um uh you can get overtunes of the
fundamental so
we he has made some uh pictures with 40
nanometer light wow coherent light
generated in in the laser you're saying
this a terawatt laser yeah that's that's
because
the the pulses are very short some under
50 seconds yeah wow that's absolutely
incredible and what what would be a
technical application for that well for
the moment we are just studying the
principles and see what what is possible
what's possible to do yeah yeah worry
about the applications later on just get
the results right first yeah we yeah
there's always something to do with
something yeah we hope uh I mean you you
go into interesting uh wavelength
regions so
mhm so we hope in the
future well Sven is there anything you'd
like to add to the interview before we
close it
out what would you like to say if you
had a chance to say there's going to be
a lot of people listening to you okay I
I I would like a lot of people to come
here and do some color hologram okay and
how would they go about doing that I
don't I don't know for the moment I will
find
out I guess the first step would be for
them to contact you right yeah yeah and
I will have a a link to your uh website
on The holot Talk page and if you send
that document to me I also include that
document as a download yeah okay and if
anybody would like to do color
holography now would they have to
actually attend the University in order
to do color holography I I will find out
a way
to I think if if I get a lot of people
interested in it maybe we can uh arrange
an international course that would be
very nice that would be very nice once
again I okay well well I'm glad we
finally got a chance to speak to one
another yes and was very nice talking
with you it's very nice talking with you
it's very beautiful work that you're
doing I wish uh I wish I could have more
experience with color holography or even
just see one because it's been so many
years I I'd love to see one in front of
me because I imagine they must be
breathtaking oh yeah oh
yeah and the the color I mean the plates
that I makes are very
clear and that that's very I mean you
you you think the object is just
behind in full color which which was the
whole point of holography really I mean
you see a monochrome image uh Yeah you
sort you certainly do get that sense and
of course of course we have a pseudo
color as well which if if done properly
can give you very much a sense of color
within the image but I imagine true
color holography must be mindboggling I
remember seeing one I think it was a
Japanese hologram that I saw in uh
Montreal when I was there and it just um
I just could not believe it yeah I I I
have a a nice setup to to do pedoc color
Holograms too mhm mhm but I think there
there is one hologram or
so which isocol in
the on the website yeah do you sell any
of the Holograms no that I I haven't I I
haven't uh done that if someone went to
your website and they wanted to buy one
of those color Hol GRS would you sell it
to
them well it's possible maybe yes yeah
if the price was right I guess right
yeah well I I mean most of the Holograms
you I don't have more than some few yeah
just one or two I guess yeah same with
me so so we also have had some some uh
exhibitions mhm yeah we have a group
here that uh is interested in holography
and sometimes we we uh decide to make an
exhibition so yeah that's uh yeah if you
sawell the Holograms you wouldn't be
able to do the exhibitions no because
you wouldn't have them anymore okay well
I want to thank you San it's been very
nice talking with you and I want to wish
you a a nice weekend I guess your
weekend's getting started mine is still
have some time before I start mine it's
only 1 in the afternoon here but it was
very nice talking with you and uh look
forward to having your show up and I'm
sure the listeners are going to enjoy it
as well okay yeah right very nice to to
speak with you very nice all right thank
you very much thank you very much too
bye okay bye
bye